you know I this is a really good
a good I would say jumping-off point
sure conversation because there's a your
you know we were just talking about your
current partner yeah about four years
and and you're talking about how thick
he was right
or did sure oh yeah she's incredibly be
a person and I mean I mean she I mean I
think I don't think there's a it I don't
think it's a coincidence that I've been
really working on this notion of the
inexhaustible yeah as the way of
disclosing reality and the relationship
I have with her I'm going to keep
referring to her neutrally because I
don't think she'll want her name may be
public yeah
and so I hope people understand that
that doesn't mean any impersonality on
my part towards her but yeah I had like
I said that sense of the inexhaustible
Ness she's incredibly deep and like I
say and I don't mean just intellectually
what she is but especially spiritually
and emotionally and she's this is an
inadequate word she I find her so deeply
mature her ability to bring a kind of
wisdom to bear on situations and but but
in a messed with you know with
vulnerability so it calls out she she's
reliably capable of calling out the very
best in me and she tells me that I do
the same for her and so that it's been
it continues to be a very very profound
experience I believe for both of us
so yeah it's the the way in which we're
a measure to get I really mean this all
of these terms have been rendered trite
right now because of our mass marketing
of and our over emphasis on romantic
relationships but you know if we just
pop it was again what what I also heard
and sure
I heard a few different things like one
is one is I heard depth very much
inexhaustible capacity for wisdom yes
and the ability to call out yes but of
course you hear me saying these all
analytically but they're not right they
are all just yeah different facets and
aspects of the same thing which for lack
of a better term and I don't mean any
commitment to a Christian Cartesian
metaphysics but this is Sarah's soul and
as I was about to say I find her my soul
mate and here we connect that sort of
the foundations of our psyches in a
really profound and profoundly
nourishing way and so like I said I I
mean I would admire saw if I just knew
her as a friend
because she's such an incredibly decent
and people I said her name I said I
wasn't going to incredibly a decent and
deep person so the fact that I I feel
they're privileged to be in a
relationship with her and that's how it
feels every day I mean we have our
conflicts everybody does because we're
human beings more complex and were all
wounded and traumatized by our pasts
great but what I what I what I have
found is and this is this is engendered
a deep trust I found that we are both
capable of being vulnerable about our
flaws and bringing them to real
discussion results in something more
than just reconciliation when there's
been conflict it's more like a sense of
a deeper reconnection in virtue of
having discussed through the conflict
and the issues please don't
misunderstand me I don't I don't promote
myself as any kind of advisor there
about romantic relationships
I'm just trying to honor its you for
your questions all right
nicely and and and try to do justice to
this amazing person that I'm Way right
it's well actually what I'm hearing you
say is is not actually it's actually
you're making a link between your
connection was with her that you're that
that's actually connecting to your work
in the world right now
Oh tremendously even to your interest
even when it's coming like in a certain
sense your relationship and and she is
inspiring forth
the what what you're seeing yeah very
much
saying and what you're communicating in
the world very much I mean so I mean
first of all not just as a partner
sorrows sorry she's tremendously
important supportive she's just really
supportive and but she calls forth from
me there there's no other way of putting
it because it's not something I can
provoke or instigate she calls forth for
me yeah the best poetry I've ever
written sort of some of the most um I
don't know what to call it not the most
insightful philosophical mmm
realizations yeah it's like I say these
words these words that we've crafted
they seem to fail
I mean she's more I mean she's my best
friend but she's more than a friend I
mean you're a good friend and I
appreciate that and you know I value it
with what we are what we are cultivating
together I value it very deeply and so
don't misunderstand what I'm about to
say but foot sorry it's it's at a level
that it's a level beyond that and and
it's it's it's for both of us it's it
brings with it therefore a challenge
it's it's an odd thing to say that
something so good is challenging
precisely because it is so good because
you know the brain is a prediction
machine and it prefers predictable
unhappiness predictable and happiness
over surprising happiness definitely
prefers predictable unhappiness over
surprising happiness it's just like
right and so and so it's like oh this is
a problem the brain is good well this is
a problem you're so happy right and I
don't mean Goethe
you know I mean happy in the sense of a
deep sense of connectedness and meaning
right and so the brain you know your
frame problematizes it and then it it
tries to turn what I think is a pseudo
problem because if it's the
unfamiliarity of the goodness into a way
of trying to say well you know this is
like something from the past in which
you got hurt and so we talk about those
kinds of things a lot we bring it up we
bring out you know that how that if
you'll allow me the sunlight of the
goodness cast the shadow of doubt and as
the sunlight gets more intense that the
shadow seems to darken in a
corresponding manner and you have to
keep you have to we keep reconnecting to
each other and that's tricky right
because you're trying to express there's
need with the need we all have without
deifying the person in any way or ray of
finding the person in any way and you
know and to to deeply connect well also
really about safing and caring about the
person's autonomy so these are all
things that again as you get as you want
to get I find at least as you want to
get so much closer to a person all of
the existential tensions that Tillich
and Heidegger and kirkegaard even that's
what you talk about they get highlighted
and they get that the energy of the
relationship and pregnat them and they
vibrate more and more and more and so
you have to if you have to give date you
have to get together and turn that
vibration into sort of a dance that
keeps you sort of resonating with each
other is it I think what I'm hearing you
say is that the difference because I
would imagine that those existential
tensions can come up and they can be the
beat when they come up they can be the
beginning of the end of a relationship
or the beginning of of it's possible
flourishing yes and I think what I am
I'm hearing you say is if there's some
kind of connection between the
difference that makes a difference to
vulnerability oh very much so I mean
I have found I mentioned this to you
before that my trust is usually
engendered when I sense that somebody is
willing to color you know calibrate with
me their degree of vulnerability I mean
you don't want to be super vulnerable in
every interaction because that's not
appropriate
right but with somebody who is going to
see the depths of my vulnerability it
they she creates great trust to me
because she brings up and expresses a
similar corresponding vulnerability and
I do and I don't mean that in a needy
sort of vampiric fashion in which she's
trying to you know save me or anything
like that no that's where the maturity
there's a the the maturity gives her a
centeredness so that vulnerability is
never something that is draining me it's
it's more something like I said what it
does for me is it tends to engender a
profound kind of resonant trust yes yes
the and it's and so that what I'm also
hearing too in this and this also
harkens to me like things I've been
thinking about myself for years and
noticing and making sense of is this
you've just made this connection between
I really appreciated between like these
existential tensions right that that the
route that your relationship can be will
one is they inherently bring them all
right very much very much but the
relationship can be a like bring them up
and they can be a crucible right is that
what the word to use like the crucible
so I did use it but it's a good word and
like in a certain set in the Tillich
sense of the word or the existential
sense of the word of being the the the
the mechanism of their transformation or
the covering up in the demise right I
think so I mean again I'm very wary of
holding myself up as any kind of
authority on this because yeah
but yeah I think that's very much the
case I mean part of what I've thought
about this is perhaps part of the
confusion I mean there's a lot of other
historical reasons so I'm not saying
this is the sole cause and part of the
confusion I think people get into the
romantic relationships where they try to
elevate them to the status of God or
something like that yeah is is to convey
I mean I'll use of philosophical
language here it's to confuse a
criterion with with with an entity right
the the these relationships they call up
into our awareness some of our you know
some of our deeper deepest existential
structures right I think we can we can
therefore confuse that of their ability
to call them up and accentuate them with
thinking that they are the source and
the remedy you have those structures and
I think and and so people I think
sometimes confuse the intensity of the
feeling yeah of these of the grammar of
our ontology or personal anthologies
right with the idea that well that the
relationship is the generator and the
sustainer and and and the resolver of
these and I think that's a fundamental
mistake I think that's a very
fundamental mistake yeah yeah totally
and it's and it is and knapping the case
at the same time if we if we relate to I
would imagine this is part of the
vulnerability that you're talking about
right is is I come to you and I realize
I realize where I fall short
I realize where I imagine that you fall
short I see my own judgments my own
criticisms my own and I see yours on
some on some level and that there's
there's a way in which that if I can
because my you know there's a big
difference I think between vulnerability
and and exposure is that experience of
being exposed which usually has it
elements of that's usually the kind of
stuff that traumatize this that's racket
here you know you're in play guard and
your friends come up behind you do they
pull your pants down and there you are
exposed and then you know you know 10
years of therapy to kind of get over
that
yeah exposure usually brings shame
totally and then there's owner ability
which i think is what I'm I think is
what I'm hearing you talk about here in
your relationship is that there's like
oh I've been more vulnerable ie I've
been more willing to volunteer to share
what's difficult for me to share and
revealing myself right even if even if
my experience of you is I feel it
revealed
I would actually still violent I
wouldn't I invited on some level or a
volunteer yeah it's a difference in the
quality of the attention seconds
eventually me but you just say you just
broke up like yeah if not in the first
few seconds eventually and yeah yeah I
mean there's a phenomenological
difference right there's a felt
difference in the attention that your
disc let's use the word disclosure to be
neutral between exposure and
vulnerability there seems to be a
phenomenological difference in the
attention to your disclosure
whereas if an exposure there's a sense
of a violation almost violence of a
penetration right into an area of
weakness that could potentially be
exploited whereas when I what I instead
what I I feel with what you're calling
vulnerability and I'm green with that
term the the attention that appeals
instead nourishing it feels like yes
this is this this hurts or this is
wounded but it's it's not probative in
the sense of well maybe I can exploit
this weakness it's instead well here's
here's a way in which we can deeply
connect and here's how you know I can
allow you perhaps to use me as a mirror
to reflect upon that that wound or that
that hurt and so it's much more than
that I feel when I'm doing it with her
that but that's it's she's acting like
this beneficent mirror and I don't mean
that in a dismissive fashion I need
in a sense that and instead of it being
the hungry gays that is exceeding
seeking exploitation its instead the
mindful me here that that's allowing me
to look and reflect upon this from a
different in a different way in a
different angle she's a master at that
and I mean that as a compliment she can
often get me to restructure my thinking
when I'm in the some of the depths of my
wounds that I find extremely affording
of me moving changing going to it going
to a different place than I've always
been it she says I do the same for her
and I have reason to believe this is
true and so this is part of what we
regularly do with each other hmm Wow Wow
there's a there's a quality there's
something there that just really
highlight something really rich which I
believe is what part of what Christopher
and I were talking about oh that was an
amazing conference uh he oh my gosh he
is so lyrical and articulate and the
depths that he brings up so effortlessly
just it's like you know somebody's
churning the depths of you know the
Pacific Ocean and stuff comes to the
surface so readily for him this is so
impressive
totally yeah and in one of the things he
kept highlighting is after this
conversation with with him that you're
right you know him just expressing his
thoughts are they do they arrive in
articulation at least in that
conversation in the conversation I the
other conversation I saw with him in
Paul was a certain level of a lyrical
disc but like it that expresses a such
deeply existential and and religious yes
religious structures just fell out of
him right I deeply respect finding
myself landed in that sense and I think
one of the things that you're talking
about is one of the things he really
highlighted what was this quality of
just in the most basic forms of
listening and speaking
and this one how mysterious
that is right just the act the simple
act of the most common thing that we do
all day long which is we talk to each
other right yeah if you look at it but
if you what I really kind of got from
that conversation is like if you look at
just that in itself and you actually
just really look at it it becomes more
and more mysterious right and it's in
the ontological sense of mystery yeah I
mean yeah very much I mean that's what I
meant were about the inexhaustible nurse
and if I mean yeah I mean there's one
sense philosophically theoretically and
I argue for this in some of my videos
and this is you know Blake's idea to see
a world in a grain of sand you know
every every lack of a better word
everything or every object has that
potential for us we we could find
anything because everything is
ultimately combinatorially explosive and
what it is I find I've coined this term
and thought the thing in itself or the
thing beyond itself
everything is always beyond itself right
and so you're not but there's something
about and I do have those experiences I
guess you'd call the mystical
experiences of nature or coming across a
beautiful object or sometimes it's just
in deep some annotation of the
experience of the breath or the sense of
life so I do have those but there's
there's a quality that is and this is
something that I'm exploring and it's
work I'm doing on the next series about
dialogue and dialectic right there's a
quality that comes in there it's almost
like the third man factor that they talk
about where you know people get when
they're you know these expeditions and
they sort of hallucinate mutually
hallucinate this this third presence
that's there but there's this element in
dialogue and I've been reading a lot
about it and trying to get that that
which is given Steinbach in his book on
the phenomenology of mysticism
phenomenology misses to me he's trying
to talk about this
he's trying to talk about the is the his
argues that phenomenology is about
trying to trying to get oneself in a
place where one can receive how things
are giving themselves right it's similar
to Heidegger's galazy night but he talks
about that in in this if i don't like
this term but we don't have better ones
this mystical aspect right there's an
intensive a there's an intense kind of
givenness because there's all these
things we can do at which we can provoke
we can make right and and so we have
this direct causal ability to provoke
and but then there's there are these
things that we we can't provoke them and
Platonists talks about this right you
can't provoke the one into disclosing
itself for a period you can do a lot to
make yourself receptive but its
disclosure is self present saying that
is that is always a gift because it is
it is beyond right and be hard to be
careful here I don't want people miss
reading me or misunderstanding me but
it's beyond your sort of agency in your
sense you can't provoke it into
existence
hey so it's like is it fair to say so
that I think I your act I think what I
think what you're talking about I'll ask
you this is the way that that which
can't be provoked right in your
existence in the in the dialogue is that
that what happens what for example when
when you call when you when you name
something in the dialogue at that moment
where you where we realize that we're
both what's doing the talking what we're
talking about is what's doing the
talking yes great those moments of like
oh where the logo straight you're
talking about the Lord all of a sudden
do the logos is speaking right right now
but there's this quality where that it I
didn't know it and till it all we were
already in it right yes yes like no you
said it I wasn't recognizing that that
in fact was happening but there's
something about that is so intriguing to
me about
that the most important thing that we
would want to be able to point to and
just happen and provoke that even if we
tried to do that if it was if it that we
find ourselves already inside of it
begun right that we couldn't provoke has
this quality of not recognizing it until
we're already in it are they there's a
deep reason for that because I think I
think and this is the Platini an idea
but ultimately like is only known by
like there's sort of the core of the
conformity theory I don't think you can
recognize the logos except by means of
being immersed in the logos I think
that's the original that's one of the
thrusting insights are in the whole
Platonic tradition that right you can't
recognize the logos until the logo sees
itself presence because the logos puts
you into alright the very state by which
it's it's it's recognition as possible
it's the self presencing of the logos
that makes it possible for it to be you
know free it for it to become present to
you it's a it's a it's a grounding thing
it's very much like you know if you are
incapable of love right you can't
recognize it in other people use you
have to be in love to some degree to
really recognize the love in another
person these things this is what I mean
by their being participatory we don't
make them we don't merely receive them
we're not passive victims we're not you
know we're not you know purely active
architects we me right we we conform to
them we embody them but we also right
reach out to them and are called forth
by them these are all the things that
are you know the this is this is what I
mean I think the deal logos is a way of
trying to make multiple people mutually
receptive to the participation in the
logos and and that's a that's a very
tricky thing and one of the things that
I thought that gets lost is when
Aristotle takes the logos in turns to
turn it into logic
all right then we lose logic is
important and I am NOT a person that
denigrates logic but what one of the
things we lose is because logic is
something that over which we can
exercise this mastery right you get this
control right we lose that we lose
something important I mean err slow is
trying to capture the normativity of the
logos the way it draws us and compels us
and how it calls us towards truth and
and that's that that's what was good in
the logic I get that but something is
being lost what you called I guess
perhaps the mystery but what I want to
say is this their sense of right
participating in something right that
takes on a life of its own but it's like
agape that's why the Christians linked
them is so readily agape and logos
because it precedes us even though it
seems to take on a life of its own
between us
like you said Sooners were in the
recognition of it we we recognize that
it has preceded us and grounded and
afforded that very you know that that
very I don't that emergence yes sorry
that was that was a bit of a speech but
there's so much going on there that I'm
trying like this is what I was diving
deeply into right now as I work on the I
work on the next series that I really
I'm trying to understand all these
dimensions of dialogue and dialectic and
you know the differences that came after
and all that just I'm trying to get at
and I see like when I saw the two talks
do your two talks recently the one you
had with Chris and the one you had with
Jordan Hall both of those were like ah
there's stuff going on there there's
stuff going on there and you know I just
like what I want it like what I'm trying
to get at
yeah is is there's something here yeah
with like with what you're doing with
the circling and then and and but and I
want to see how how is that because this
is our challenge how do we get back sort
of what Aristotle rightfully found but
perhaps a little bit I don't want to say
mistakenly extricated from but how do we
bring back into yeah the circling the
argumentation in the Phil
Safa consent how can we do philosophy
together right with the circling so the
dialogue becomes the dialectic yeah
right and that's what I'm trying to like
how do how do we get them to talk to
each other because it's not a simple
case of well here's its essence and
here's its essence and I just stick them
together because that's exactly what
would be thwarted right but it's like
see you see I'm gesturing in this grass
being reaching fashion but you know can
I can we bring in the argumentation back
and I see people my good friend Peter
Lambert trying to do this right he's
trying to get like with his ideas about
the anti debate and stuff like that he's
trying to say can we get something like
the authentic relating and the argument
patient should have back together again
so they're mutually facilitating and
affording each other and I see this is
this is the core of the project that I'm
trying to that I'm wrestling with right
now right so that though I so there's
part of the pot like part part of the
core of it is you're skiing it and this
is one of the things I wanted to ask you
just about is in some level like we're
we're this conversation right now for me
is I'm hearing questions I had in other
other conversations that I've recently
had that you've watched right yes one of
the things I'm noticing is I'm watching
myself I'm going okay do the people that
may be that are watching know what I'm
referring to because they're so present
I have to keep an eye on that because
it's so there's so with other covers and
I just heard a way in which they're
deeply present to you and the meat-like
part of why they're present is that
they're evoke the thing that you're
trying to look at right now like you're
seeing possible movies of a glimmering
kind of glimmering forth and it's kind
of like in this moment you're like yeah
you can tell you can tell I'm the middle
of it I yes I feel voluntarily and
turned by you well well hope it's like
hope it's like you know from the Hindu
mythology we were able to churn the
cosmic milk into butter or something
like that
I mean it feels it doesn't feel
fruitless it feels fruitful what's
happening at me right now and the work
I'm doing and the residence I'm seeing
and I see again like I watched a very
good discussion between David fuller
David Thornton and Mike I don't remember
Michaels name future yeah from the
beater yeah and and they're really in
there they're doing something sorry this
work sounds dismissive and it's not so
please charity on this word they're
trying to do something we're practical
right right in that they're trying to
figure out they feel the pulse of this
change and that there's they're trying
to figure out the practices that will
catch the current the Kairos of this
change and hopefully tap into it and
afford it that they see happening in
discourse and dialogue and and it's and
like I say I feel that the project I'm
engaged in right now is so resonant that
with what they're talking about I feel
like I feel a kind of an urgency to it
precisely because of that it's like yeah
this this is this is the Kairos this is
this is what's happening we need to get
you know more articulation both in the
sense of linguistic art in theoretical
articulation but also articulation in
our actions in our practices we need to
well we need to keep moving both of
those forward together and I think this
is very exciting and like I said well
you and I are both talking to Jordan
Jordan Hall is trying to put together
get more more of us talking together and
working on trying to understand this
it's it's all very exciting but to see
these you know I include you in this
right and I try to include you as much
as I can and this product you're
valuable and important to it but all
these people have tremendous talent and
expertise and depth you know coming
together and really trying to you know
do that it sounds so simple but do the
thing you're pointing to they they want
to get to the point where they can step
back and somehow articulate and you know
Abe in the biblical
sense of naming what it is that we're
doing right now yes right what is what
we're all wrestling with something right
and we're all wrestling profoundly and
people what is it what is it what is it
and we keep asking this and we should
keep asking it right and there's a sense
in which and this is where we really got
to you in the conversation with with
with Jordan Hall the one that I've had
with him so far this omote where it we
felt so in the tension of at least I was
very I think both of us were very
present to this recognition of to name
it in a certain sense in such a way that
it that it was there's a danger in
naming it that it could go into that yes
yes hate the logic if you will the logic
the logos just that awareness of that
danger and it was just really great
being with him both of us being ever
increasingly aware of that danger but
Sunday dancing with it in such a way
that that that awareness itself allowed
it to be it to emerge right like so so
something something about what Heidegger
maybe because this thought is of all all
the things I've ever read of Heidegger
um I'm sorry let me just turn this off
here so we can not be disturbed by the
social media hang on one second do not
disturb okay yeah so there's this just
this sense of of where we're I think
Heidegger talked about this one thing
that I've been thinking about for 20
years since I've been reading him which
is where he he frames where he's framing
a lecture he's about to give and I think
it's like for the death of Heisenberg or
or some assists or something and he and
he starts off the lecture and he talks
about that you know perhaps we should
want to listen to the to the work of the
person who were celebrating their deaths
over and over and over
again and and and it would be wise for
us not to to demand immediate
intelligibility right very much right
like if the painter was here right and
and we were standing before the work
like his painting like with him we
should want to look at it for a long
time and still not demand that it be
immediately intelligible us and he kind
of goes through these things in which it
highlights a kind of obviousness where
it seems so sensible to to have a
sensible response and not having that
demand which are few like we start we we
have a we have a listening that doesn't
isn't apt to listen to the world that
way most of the time but there's still a
few places right and then he then he
brings it into philosophy which is this
world right which is like we not so with
philosophy you know we seem to demand
that it be immediately graspable and
even in service of giving us the good
life right and then ago tonight he says
like perhaps philosophy is speaking to
that that which is both determinate to
the philosopher the poet and and the
scientist which is to realize that the
question of being is still not yet
articulated right and he goes he goes on
okay now let me give you a hint on how
to listen to the lecture which is
interesting just in itself that there's
ways that we listen first of all is just
can be mind-boggling when you really
look at it and it says instead of
listening to a series of propositions
perhaps we can follow the movement I'm
showing yes I think that's I think
that's a very important thing so a
couple things I want to say in response
first of all when you talked about a
question that you've been thinking about
for twenty years abroad a deep smile to
my face because I think I mean your
exemplifying I think what you're talking
about
the ability to stay with something which
I mean there's a way you can
misunderstand that and I don't think
this is what you're saying there's a way
of what you're in which people say
people can confuse staying with
something like whether you stay in a
relationship and think about there's
always that danger and you shouldn't
demand too much intelligibility yes too
fast from your partner right there's
that there's that okay so think about
not confusing staying with something
with being stuck because those aren't
the same being stuck is like when you
you have that all right there's the lock
and you can't move and there's right
whereas that when you're staying with
something it's not so much you know it's
not maybe questioning is the wrong weird
is more like questing right that what
you're staying with it you're staying in
the question you're staying with it
more and more more and more happens
right like it and I only mean this fine
analogy but again you get into a central
partnership with the phenomenon that I
have with with with my partner yeah and
it's so there there's people can't and
and this is one of the great mistakes
when people look at philosophies is well
you know because yes start talking about
this stuff for hundreds of years well
you know and you're so slow and it's
like well some problems take centuries
to discuss and and some relationships
take years real years before you start
to get a sense of what's going on in
them and it's you know and and and I
think I think that's what Heidegger is
pointing to and it's the same thing with
Plato Plato in the seventh letter says
you know you read all this stuff
including his own work he says but you
have to live with somebody for a long
time until the spark and there you can't
make it you have to make yourself
receptive to it until the spark catches
between two people and then then he says
then you'll understand my philosophy
yeah and I think that dwelling with that
we find when we stay with somebody in a
partnership that's not if that's not the
dry barren stuckness but is actually
this fecund
oh I think that's what he's trying to
talk about and and and and the trick of
it is for me I guess is I mean I'm an
educator and I'm a scientist so I have
to try and bring theoretical clarity to
this topic that I want to discuss that's
part of what I have to do yeah and I but
and I have to do it right but so I have
I have a sitch I haven't I have a
condition on me that you don't face when
you're encircling yeah in that I have to
in addition to you know yeah fully
participating in it and you know that
I'm joining a circling group and things
like that and doing these kinds of
conversations with you and Jordan for
example and Chris yeah but in addition
to that I also have to try and I have to
bring a theoretical articulation to it
that isn't actually properly part of it
but nevertheless has to be wedded to it
in the appropriate manner yeah that's
that's that's the that's the that's the
tricky thing like we people are craving
a language like often say it like a
vocabulary grammar to talk about this
one what is it we're doing this dialogue
deal logos dialectic you know this this
transformative discourse within you know
distributed cognition what is it we're
doing how does it work right right it
and and and I'm very I'm very sensitive
to your concern and that's why I use the
biblical sense of naming we don't want
to name it in an idolatrous fashion we
don't want to name it such that we think
that by maybe if we can summon it at
will yes right but at the same time and
again we don't want to have a premature
intelligibility but on the other hand we
don't want to leave people bereft right
that's thanks that's that's the trick
that's the trick so that so right there
just even like that you use that that
yeah metaphor trick trickster right
herim playfulness yeah romantic right
good quality of like in what I what's
interesting about Burmese myth
mythically so hermes is that my
understanding is the God that is he's
not he's not totally a God and he's not
totally human
so he's he's not he's he's the one with
the wings on it on on the ankles and on
the head right so Hermes is like her met
her munetaka phenomenology is this place
it is it doesn't totally go above weds
yeah and isn't wedded at the same time
and transcends both earth and heaven
right yes yes in this way this
in-between way which is Oh like he's a
vehicle for transformation continually
right exactly
and in what's really interesting about
Hermes and I I heard this I think
through through Hillman although I
haven't been able to find it in the
actual myth so I don't know if it's
actually true but it makes sense if it
is which is where Hermes has been wedded
to is Hestia which is the goddess of
Dumas domesticity that Hillman kind of
draws up psychologically this is like
but when Hermes when when Hermes isn't
in its in its right place it becomes
manic in a Devoy it becomes divorced of
Hestia where Hermes is just this forever
which I think you could say some would
say is like post-modernism right in the
in that sense of the word just the
spinning off of like forever
interpretations but with no sense of any
ground or recognition of ground that
that the sense of home and domesticity
of regularity of I think and right
because I think it's it's it's great I
hope the myth is true yeah you cut
because I mean I think part of I mean
Chris and I argue this in the book and I
argued it in a series I think part of
what sacredness is is to have again what
at this top toe knows there's an
existential tension between that which
homes us yeah
and that which exposes us to the
numinous the sacred right is that which
the experience of sacredness is to be
constantly you know in tension between
these because I think that that's sort
of the that sort of powerful higher
order elements
realization you've got the part that's
assimilating right and Strack ting what
can be held as invariant but you've got
the part that's constantly varying
opening you up to the numinous the
unexpected and and and and the thing is
like Hermes and Hestia right but many of
our sacred symbols they have this polar
tension within them precisely because
right there you know they're know they
they home no think of Zeus Zeus you know
he defeats the monsters with his
lightning bolt in homes the world for
mankind but he's also the capricious
deity that can suddenly loose the
lightning bolt at you right
so the numinous and and and the homing
are always there it reminds me of a line
from CS Lewis Paul Van Dyck they were
like this where where the children are
talking about ozland hmm and and one of
the kids says well is it is he tame and
they go oh goodness no he's not tamed
but he's good all right he's numinous
he's not tamed but there's a part but
he's good he contributes to the homing
there's the two are always there
together and this is exactly what I'm
trying to get is like I want to talk
about this right right in a way in which
you know I one of the ways here that is
what I want to say sorry you're helping
me a lot
one of the ways in which we could be
premature in our we could we could we
could grasp that premature
intelligibility would be to simply try
to resolve the tension yeah with some
kind of Pat definition or method some
algorithmic rule or procedure alright
and that's not what you need to do with
the theory the theory needs to
articulate the tension so that it can be
creatively participated into its depths
that's what I'm looking for yeah what's
it like just to what I heard you said
when he said yeah oh you're helping me
here particulate right like what's it
just like having just articulated it
your project it felt like a path opened
up yeah that's exactly like from my
chest a path opened up it and you and I
are together on it
right that's what it felt like it felt
like that that's awesome
that when you talked about that tension
hold articulate it right to articulate
the attention the question the dialogue
right and also what you talked about I
really I really felt at the moment you
said it was yeah there's the coming
coming at this from as a professor and a
scientist right my job right very much
you is almost in some ways is is almost
never attainable but you found a what
thing I'm appreciating and I think so
many people so deeply appreciate about
you right and both about you personally
and also what comes through you right is
this this deep fidelity right to a lot
as you talked about is a lot is to face
the mystery and really look at the
mystery and be technical technically
precise while not solving the mystery as
it right but to articulate the mystery
in such a way that we find ourselves
more and more intelligently involved in
it right and right which is under singer
I think I I think I just appreciated it
like in a big way I like more than I
have before more than I and I think I
did before but there's a way to just
really hit me in that moment of oh yeah
like not only not only are you up to the
task that many of us have been up to it
but there it is it there is actually um
you're looking at subjects where you
have a lot of scrutiny
right or at least a history of a gaze of
scrutiny for technical decision on the
very thing that demands ray it not be
concealed in that precision it's just I
think I just really felt there the risk
there is beauty that's doing if there is
and that's why the word you use fidelity
really rang with me that was a very alia
there's a really really appropriate word
really saying to what's happening right
here yeah it's it's it there's a kind of
carefulness right which it's it's it's
not a confusion of words you want to
avoid it's a confusion of modes of
intelligibility right there's there
there there's theorizing and it has its
role in its place and then that's
different from actually undergoing
transformation and so I try to I try to
help myself and help the people that I'm
teaching or talking with to try and not
confuse them together I often say don't
confuse properties of your theory with
properties of what your theories about
and vice versa
so that's that that's a tremendous
responsibility that we need to pay much
more careful attention to I think just
generally everybody needs to pay much
more careful attention to not engaging
in that kind of confusion not thinking
that your mode of intelligibility is has
to be the same right as to share the
properties with the thing you're talking
about at all times and so that that's a
very tricky thing so I mean you want to
write this freaked out one of the
examples I uses sometimes you need to
write really clear prose about the
deepest poetry and that's and and you
will not do a good job if you just write
another poem because you'll just defer
people in their attempts to understand
poetry but on the other hand you can't
just make it a dry analysis right you
got it
you got to do it's got to have the
clarity that nevertheless evokes alright
it calls out it gets right it's in that
creative
nation ship with the poem that's sort of
how the analogy I used in my mind
there's the police Asst of relevance
realization and sense-making and then
there's the theory which is the prose
and they're trying to get that those two
to like Michael eight like I say like
somebody who's writing a really clear
you know insightful prose essay about a
poem by Rilke alright and and you know
and and and and and it's not another
poem right but it's not independent from
the you see what I'm trying to get at
its wedded to the pole in the right way
yeah uh yeah just that this wedded miss
mm-hmm right this wedding this tonally
well I think that's what that's why I
think you know you know that's why the
biblical notion for knowing is there off
you know which implies sexual
intercourse this is how you're supposed
to know God and I don't mean anything
pornographic by it I mean it's that
wedded Ness right wedded nests or like
tasting taste and see that the Lord is
good right I'm not a Christian or
anything you know that but those
metaphors right again about you know
because taste is the is the sense that
weds us to something yeah yeah taste and
wetness so so there's also a quality in
taste here is that the ad there is that
quality where someone who has good taste
seems to be the taste is defined being
of taste
having taste seems to be defined in what
it is impregnated in its absence right
so it's like when someone who has good
taste it seems to me versus someone who
doesn't have a good taste right is
they'll come to a to a situation and
they'll be able to draw out and be
impregnated by yes yes rightly all of
the multiple relations that are
available versus someone who doesn't
will eat the same meal that will not be
impregnated by so it's I think what I'm
hearing you say is this is it is it fair
to say that the theory in which calls
that's called forth through the mystery
that one sees or the poet
right that writes the poem and the
listening that can hear it that the list
there's a certain way that like
listening can call forth a theory that
is part of B being allowing one to be
able to taste all the foods at the poet
yeah hey think about the connoisseur and
notice how that's a French word for
knowing right think about the
connoisseur they they bring an
articulate not just in thought they
haven't are right they big in
articulation at is a discerning ability
to discriminate right between aspects
and features and structures within what
they're tasting so the connoisseur right
unfolds right but that doesn't mean that
the words can capture what it is to
taste the wine you have to still taste
the wine right what they do is they they
write it this articulation like I said
it's weighted and I like you were to
impregnate it's like it opens it up so
that the structure in the wine through
the experience of the taste actually
transforms you know our perspective of
knowing in a deep well and I think yeah
that's what that's what I that's what
I've been trying to do you know I with
my series it's like I don't want to
explain away that's not what I'm trying
to do you know I'm not I'm critical of
kinds of musical positions and things
like that but I do I very much want to
try and like I said I want to give a
theory that that that bleeds into the--
oriya right that the theater theory they
the explanatory structure leaves you
into the OREA in that sense of that
participatory contemplation of things
Wow
Furion well that's why I have the words
on my tattooed on my leg I have a word
that basically you know means sort of
theory and then into the-- oriya you
want it yeah i I've succeeded if I've
led somebody through good theory into
deep the OREA huh-huh
that's that's my criterion of success
yeah
I think I'm I think you're leading me
into the-- oriya right now we're doing
it for each other I think yeah yeah
which is I would imagine as part of
the-- oriya yes it is part of what we
can't quite tell who's doing who - what
right very much and so does one of the
things I'm trying to explore what's the
relation because Don electic has these
two meanings in the applauded tradition
it means something done in dialogue with
people yeah but they're also it right
and and but it also connects to theoria
and that it's also something you do with
being you go through the Ann agog a
through dialectic as well so there's
deep connections between theoria and
deal logos I need to be unpacked and
explored and that's also something
because there's like there's a
horizontal and a vertical dimension to
dialectic and they're always deeply
inter penetrating and inter affording
each other right right Wow
so I'm so I'm so part of what I'm
imagining so I'm trying to imagine being
you right okay having you're like I'm
sure there's a lot but being someone who
actually has somebody permanently on
their body right this tattooed from
theory to fiora right that
transformational release realization and
then watching the conversations you have
that you're having not just watching
watching the lectures that you're giving
right and then watching also the
conversations that you're both having
with people ray of which I think this
one's one of them and that you're
witnessing other people have many of who
are if not sourced by your dialogue in
direct relationship to the to the
meaning crisis work that you've been
doing
um so I'm just trying to be you and be
inside of this and try to try to imagine
what a day like or a week is like for
you god this is right it brings tears to
my eyes just imagining what that must be
like right for you so many ways well I
did I did similar things in my
imagination about you trying to what
it's like for you to have all these
great conversations and doing all these
circling I mean you you get to leave um
this is meant as admiration not envy we
get to live a kind of Socratic life that
I would love right and so I think that's
something I appreciate about you I
admire that
and I mean it's I mean Socrates said the
unexamined life is not worth living so I
imagine yours to be very worth living
yeah cisely because of all of these
great examinations that you all the
Socratic emulation you're doing I think
it's really really something to be
treasured um for me I mean things are
very good now again no small part due to
people like Chris and to to Sarah I've
said her name a couple times so there's
no sense trying to pretend I didn't say
but you know for a very long time
it was the Nietzschean thing for me you
know if you stare long enough into the
abyss it starts to stare back because I
was I was wrestling with the meaning
crisis for a very long time and for and
I'm sorry that's not meant to connote
that I sort of solved it or something
like that I mean I'm trying to give
people ways of responding what I met was
I was suffering the meaning crisis a
very long time in that it was
undermining my agency in at times and
powerful ways on and I think it it and
and reflection and this as well and I've
apologized to this to my previous
partners I think it impacted negatively
on my relationships I speak from
experience
when I say people can in that vampiric
fashion try to draw from the
relationships all that God and history
try to do it and when you're in the
depths of suffering the meaning crisis
that desire to draw from people can
become and I did for me become
inappropriate and too demanding I think
it I think so I think was I was hard on
people not I don't mean in a malicious
way I wasn't hard-hearted but I think it
was very hard to be around me
and so I've come to appreciate again
what a gift it is to be with sorrow to
have friends like Chris and because
precisely because they've to meet people
like you because it's all part of for me
a personal transformation when I'm when
I'm talking about trying to help people
awaken from the meeting crisis this is
not just a theoretical thing I you
Europe you're the best cut hey there hey
what happened oh my
cut my power went out like it flipped
over the switch hey we were right oh my
god you're right in a crescendo of uh
well I just I that point is still with
resonating with whatever to me it is as
I was saying the best teaching is when
you're sharing your ongoing learning
with your students and when I'm when I'm
trying to teach about awakening from the
meeting crisis because I'm going through
this personally existentially alright
and it's it's very present to my mind
what what this is of what this means and
and so I want it's what we're talking
about I want all of the theoretical work
I'm doing and I'm building this very
complex theoretical machine to use to
use our metaphor to stay wedded to the
process that I am currently within
awakening for the meeting crisis and I'm
seeing many people within and now
that's what I'm trying to do so to get
back to the point it started of all this
I you know I think now I have I have a
very good life but I don't know I don't
want to disparage my life before but I
think like I said I think I was hard on
relationships and the people that
related to me and again not maliciously
I think I can be compassionate towards
myself and say that but really we really
like the Nietzschean thing really
looking really deeply into the bits and
I think a lot of times it was looking
back out through me and people were like
oh you John is so dark so that was a
common way of talking about me
and I don't feel so dark now and so it's
the difference that's like what's the
difference such that what I'm not
hearing you say is that you're looking
any less any less of the abyss that's
right right in fact it sounds like
you're working you're looking at it even
more somehow yes but however something's
different like what's the difference I'm
no longer stuck
I'm staying with it but I'm no longer
stuck in it that's the big difference
that's what I was trying to articulate
earlier right there's a partnership in
which and you know nishitani talks about
this in religion and nothingness when
the no thingness goes from being the
stuckness the empty ended dead ending of
nihilism to the sense of the
inexhaustible that you are the off with
that's the difference that's the
difference
Wow I just wanted I want to sit with
that for a moment and really listen to
what you just said
because there's that you know as my
understanding of the way that that
socrates listened to is Damon right yes
right and listening in the sense of
midwifery hey so I it's some way what
I'm hearing you say is like there's a I
think personally we can all look at
those points where we're were that which
is feels like we're going through the
birth canal right only thing oxygen we
don't remember time you know is there
for that like the Suffocation's forever
but there's something pulling us and
then there's those moments where we're
digesting where we're actually taking
something in right where we're we're
more of the sense of the Midwife like
midwifery it's yeah right so I'm like I
mean the point of just a feeling like
we're in the presence of like midwifing
something just like right now as I'm
kind of taking and my understanding of
your life also is taking in the
understanding of that dialectic dialogue
oh s--- relationship itself like within
your life I'm also getting the logos at
the same time and everything that we're
talking to which is in some ways is
characteristic of the phenomena that
we're describing but also the phenomena
we're in right now hi in this moment but
also the moment that we're in where we
get to have these conversations and you
get to witness these conversations in
forming your work and revealing your
work to you at the same time this is why
I think when you talked when you've
texted me the other day there's been
certain moments we've texted me and I
can feel you in the integration it's
like something is really emerging here
isn't it do you feel it I'm like yeah I
totally feel it yeah I think we're
starting to articulate more of what
we're I think that what you mean when
you say that like I think so too I think
it's very much like the Socratic project
of trying to help something
I'll give birth to something to
participate in a birth you're not making
the child you're not merely receiving
the child you're again you're getting
invented in wedded and involved and a
mashed and the birthing of the child so
yeah it's very much that you're also
helping me in this dialogue to realize
how deeply in formative of my what I'm
doing right now my relationship to Sarah
is like I did I was coming to see how
deep of a template it is becoming for me
in so many ways I hadn't I mean I had a
sense of this is why I was I was using
it as a metaphor but I I didn't realize
how deeply and how deep it went all
right yeah that that's that thank you
for that that's been something it's sort
of coming more clear in my mind now and
so that this is something that I guess
is also part of what you see in the
Socratic dialectic and and and that
people miss when they just extract the
propositional arguments Socrates has a
tremendous cookie this is connoted by
the midwifery metaphor right he has a
deep capacity to deeply know often
better than they know themselves the
people he's talking with right and and
so there's that there's that deep
connectedness that drew Harlan talks
about and his work on Socrates and I see
that now there's there's there's a relay
there's a deep relationship between our
ability to relate India logos and our
ability to to connect deeply to other
people and so that sounds so trivial to
say I'm sorry but I'm trying to
articulate an insight right there's
there's a way in which the the deep
participation the deep conformity
between two people that are you know off
together it grounds and develops the
grammar that we use when we're trying to
bring
get up into like something like
philosophy yeah there's a there I've
seen how deeply those those connections
make sense what make sense what I'm
saying well I don't let me see you I
think my tears do feel like that like it
or if you can see it like like I'm
feeling move and I I I think it I felt I
don't move throughout the conversation
um I specifically when he felt moved
when you when you brought it back to the
very beginning of what we started to
talk about where you went oh I'm
starting to see when you said I'm
starting to see my relationship with
sorrow like in what you talked about was
you know that where we opened right was
was where we were talking about yeah
what it seems like that there is there
is seems to be some connection between
the depth of my relationship with her
and who I'm coming to know her to be
emulating him somehow that that
connection being tapping into the in the
inexhaustible intelligibility and then
we went through this whole diet like
this whole ride right where we were
talking about talking we were talking
about talking and coming to terms in the
the demand to come to terms in such a
way that that's that evokes that comes
that articulates the question that we
engage when more deeply right and the
unique the unique sense in your own
personal life where that has been a
that's required you to look at the the
abyss while having a sight like
scientific demands that you bring it
into technical firms but that unique
relationship that you have as a
professor as a teacher but also as a
person but all the way up to this point
where we're talking about the current
conversation that we're in that brought
it all together in this moment where you
recognize the very thing that we were
talking about in the beginning yeah all
the way through your life so here's a
moment
like what kind of walking through
walking through that like where I'm hit
by yeah I electic dialo goes the theory
the theoretical birthing the theros in
this moment in my listening it's the
fact that it's circles like that Plato
talks about that the dialogues the
dialogues often do that circle - right
it's there's something about that
communication is grounded in communing
because the community gets us to trust
in right in the open-ended feet I think
our lives make us suspicious of
conversations in ways that are permeated
into levels of our psyche that we're not
even aware of but when we when we can
when we can genuinely commune with
somebody right that communing like I
said it trains us in trust so that a
kind of communication is possible that's
not otherwise possible as I'm started
struggling to articulate but the two
words they keep singing to each other in
my mind right now is this relationship
between communication and communing and
there's something going on there right
and you know my ability to commune with
somebody very deeply because of her
depth and her maturity and her
fundamental goodness all right
has written has restored a kind of trust
in me that then permeates my ability to
communicate with others we learn more by
modeling than we do just by talking
right we really do we really really do
yeah it is it fair to say that there's
this quote that the the thing that
you're really getting it it's emerging
that's taken on some level what I'm
hearing is a lifetime right yeah it does
I mean it's some level your old life
personally but also the life of what
you've been pondering and thinking about
and can being confronted with in this
moment right now all of them on some
level are like right here to the very
tip of the thing that you're going oh
yeah what's singing to me now but when
you say singing to me now what's
interesting is what I
like literally what's the soglin's being
sung is so connected to all of that
right so it's being now is the next
level of the diet food
the yellow goes right because I'm
picking up on the one way in which the
logos differs from the logic because the
logos is the gathering of things that so
such that they come to belong together
right and so what you have is all these
things that have not yet balked and have
not yet belonged together and think
about all the relevance realization
going on there but you now gather them
up they've been gathered up so now they
now belong together and that belonging
together is the communing that makes the
communication deeper did you see that's
what I'm trying to articulate yes yes
and that and in what you're also talking
about I just want to highlight this
because me like on my side of the street
there's this quality of like I have been
trying to do that for the longest time
wit know what you're what you're
witnessing right now in with me with you
with these other conversations John I at
this level I just haven't really had
that many people to talk to
right that's talking to Jordan about
this yeah so there's this quality on one
level like yeah I've been I've been
doing courses in in this this work and a
lot of like the coursework has just
really been a function of my madness for
it right but there's a way in which most
of my philosophical inquiry with
Heidegger and the existentialists and
everyone else has been really something
that I that has been going on for me for
the most part by myself that I've been
bringing to the conversation but there's
not a lot of people that are necessarily
predisposed to being interested in this
level that we're talking about right
yeah I think that's right so there's a
way in which that that you're bringing
to light this horizon where it's not
just about as he said the other day it's
not just about agape
logos right yeah it's like the agape in
some and some level requires the
previous moving of the logos before it
for it to be able to see that to become
seers of it right there Wow to give
birth to it and that mutual autopoietic
self-transcending yet integrating what
we transcended that that that that
quality on some level what I think that
you're thinking about right now it's so
important because it's not just personal
intimacy its intimacy and that exactly
that can reveal what's worth being
intimate about right I I think that's
well said oh I had a student he was a
very good student and he said I think
your stuff of Bimini crisis is really an
intimacy crisis it's that people have
lost a sense of being able to be
intimate with reality and intimate with
what's good and what's true and what's
beautiful and then whether you were
saying that I was thinking of this and I
was hearing for some reason Paul's
saying it rather than my own voice in my
head so that's good I was hearing him
saying you know the beginning you know
in arcade logos in the beginning with
the word is right there in the beginning
is the logos you were trying to
articulate that right that the way the
logos is this sort of you know the this
arcade is foundational principle that
makes it all possible
yeah I think I I think both of those
things I don't know how they sit
together and then the third thing it was
a big thing which was Jordan Hall and I
were talking about just this and and
they all relate to each other and Oh
quick get the pattern here but it's
there right is this having you know
peers and I'm trying to do a tomb and
I'll try to pick up also that it also
means looking deeply to have peers that
we that to talk to it is very very
important
and you know getting people to
experience community in peerage I think
is a really
a fundamental thing and and and that's
again that's and that's how it's I see
you know again the disability to draw
things together so that they belong
together that's in the beginning right
and that's that's that's the ground
probity intelligibility is constantly
emerging and I think that's always
phenomenologically mysterious to us I
mean I think we can theoretically talk
about it but you can't jump outside your
framing you could ever get outside it
right there's always something you
you're always always amesh in it you can
move from frame to frame where we're not
prisoners in that sense but you can't
you can't write anything that's inside
the frame is not it's not itself the
logos right it's only what the logos has
articulated into the frame that's what I
mean when I try to talk about you know
Heidegger's main insight it but things
are constantly shining in yeah as
articulation but we also get a sense of
the deep recesses right into them you
know the depths of the logos yes the
depths of the inexhaustible Wow
so I I just keep um couple well a couple
things uh so I need to I need to go on
to my next I feel sorry for my client
cuz they're just gonna get like a boat
what I'm present to is you know perhaps
this is pop this probably plays on some
of the relationships that we're talking
about that are singing to each other so
unlock on one level there's this
experience of like yeah now you're
trying to art what I heard you say is
I'm trying to articulate what's coming
into a like just coming into being
there's something I can feel but I don't
quite it's come together for me it's
coming together as it's it's singing of
my nervous system like my nervous system
feels like it's like humming and meaning
right now and like how much so that's
like it's so full of meaning that it's
like it's pushing water out of my eyes
you know and there is this quality of of
this mysterious this mystery that's been
there for
which is how do I know to be struck by
something mm-hmm
before I understand what I'm struck by
you know in that sense I feel I feel
like I'm understanding that at a level
of feeling of where oh there's something
about the feeling of being moved where
the way that we've been communing brings
in so much richness that we're now
standing up on top of something that's
informed by what was logos which became
logic that we stood on because it was
the relationship with that we stand on
it to reveal more of it this is what I
mean when I try to say very deeply that
relevance realization is transgender
it's pre egoic it's pre-conceptual it's
before the co determination of the agent
and the arena and we can talk about it
scientifically but that doesn't mean
right that again that I've explained it
away the whole time you you were saying
what you were saying I was there's one
of my favorite scenes in Equus where
it's near the end and I start that the
therapist is saying you know yes but
explain me and he's talking about Equus
how is it that all of these things come
together and become something sacred how
does how did they come together right
and he he has a sense of this because
he's bearing witness to this epiphany
and he's and he's able to you know he
does midwifery he that's the therapy on
the same right and it's that you know
you know is that it's down these things
you know you can't you can't make a
symbol the symbol half of the symbol
house you have to you but you know
neither can you just receive a symbol if
I just give it to you it's not it hat it
has to translate
and that's part of I think what we're
deprived of you hear there's an element
again in which the articulation is an
attempt right not to just so part of it
is it is the theory into theoria but
part of it is as I say it's like it's
the respect that is to respect what
symbols are trying to be for the police
desk
and again like it's so that's what the
the Neoplatonism for me is such a
powerful template because you can see
right Plato is just he just moves
seamlessly between the poetry and the
theory and the theory those three are
just seamlessly talking to each other at
all times
Wow and that's a really important
template you need to go back and recover
not like you know the purported platonic
metaphysics or the arguments but this
this ability to get the theory the furia
and the police's mutually consonant with
each other the perfect place to complete
yes very much
so good to talk to you my good friend so
good to talk to you so I'm good to talk
to you my good friend yes mmm
many more to come oh for sure yes and
let's keep up the good text dialogues I
like those textual conversations they're
a lot of fun yeah I like the way they
come out of the balloon from you like
doesn't say what about Heidegger on this
Wow mmm take care take care take care